country folks and Shanghainese
乡下人跟上海人
but in fact, if we start counting from the population census of 1949
但其实我们说从49年的人口普查开始算啊
the actual urban residents of Beijing back then were only one million
这个北京真正城里的居民当时只有100万人
most people are actually new Beijingers
大部分人呢都是新北京人
That means after 49 years.
也就是说49年以后啊
Like our family, we moved in 43.
就像我们家虽然是43年啊
Some of the grandpa's generation came over.
一部分爷爷这辈人过来了
Then, in the early to mid-fifties,
然后呢四五几年的时候呢
people from grandma's side came over.
姥姥家这边人才过来
But we're all new Beijingers, really.
但是其实都是新北京人啊
Especially in Chaoyang District,
特别是在这个朝阳区
and Haidian District,
海淀区的
but the proportion in Chaoyang is smaller,
但朝阳区的占的比例比较小
while the proportion in Haidian is larger.
海淀区的占的比例比较多
After the 1990s,
过了90年代以后呢
the population in Beijing gradually increased,
北京的人口逐渐的啊汇集的越来越多啊
Starting from the 1990s,
到90年代开始
most people began moving to Chaoyang District,
大部分人开始就向朝阳区搬迁了
but recently, it has become Tongzhou District,
但到最近就变成了通州区
many people are buying houses in Tongzhou District,
很多人在通州区买房
I want to break a misconception here,
我要说其实有一个打破一个观念是什么呢
I will talk about this in the next three episodes,
我这三期我都会说
about the reality of breaking this misconception, what exactly does breaking a misconception mean? There are some things we consider to be established by usage. But in reality, that's not the case.
关于这个观念打破的这个事实啊 就是什么是观念的打破呢 就是有些东西我们觉得约定俗成是这样 但实际上事实不是这样
But you know,
但是大家知道啊
What does it mean to enhance cognition?
什么叫提升认知呢
Cognition is not the same as knowledge.
认知不是知识啊
Knowledge is 'knowledge',
知识是knowledge啊
Cognition is 'acknowledgment'.
认知是acknowledge
Many things are different.
很多东西是不一样的
Cognition is the process of gradually understanding how the world operates.
就是认知是你逐渐知道世界的运行的规律
It's a journey of discovery.
的这么一个过程
Cognition can draw inspiration from the thoughts of predecessors.
认知呢有从前人的思维上呢获得的灵感
One aspect is that others have already mentioned it.
一个是其实别人已经说过的东西
Another aspect of cognition is that
另外一个东西呢认知啊
practice leads to true knowledge.
实践出真知
Practice can bring new insights.
实践啊能带来新的知识
Many practices vary due to different eras, technological methods, and people involved.
很多实践因为时代啊科技手段人的不同
so each practice
所以导致每一次的实践啊
conducted at different points in time
在时间上的不同节点进行的实践呢
yields entirely different outcomes.
得到的结果是完全不一样的
Because times are changing.
因为时代在变
People evolve over time.
人也在变啊
People from 100 years ago are entirely different from those today.
100年前的人跟现在的人是完全不一样的
They are completely distinct.
人是完全不同的
Two different groups of people.
两拨人啊
Twenty years, ten years, five years make up a generation.
20年十年五年就是一代人
That's why we say practice makes perfect.
所以我们说实践出真知
It's a very reasonable statement. Speaking of which, I think it's important to note that Especially in a place like Beijing, We can say it's the new Beijingers. The town's problem solvers are the real economic and cultural hub of Beijing
是一个非常有的那个有道理的事情啊 我们要说其实我说啊这个世界上啊 特别是在北京这个地方 可以说是新北京人啊 小镇做题家才是北京的经济文化
and the center of capabilities in various fields
还有各方面的啊能力的中心啊
not these so-called old Beijingers
而不是这些我们这些所谓的老北京
the so-called original residents
所谓的原住民native people啊
Why do I say this?
为什么这样说呢
Actually, it's about multiple dimensions
其实它是分好几个维度
several layers
好几个层次的
On the surface, many people feel they lack a sense of belonging in Beijing
表面上很多人感觉我在北京没有归属感啊
unlike Shenzhen, where newcomers are immediately considered Shenzhen residents
来了就是深圳人跟深圳不一样
Shenzhen is a very vibrant and emerging city
深圳是一个非常活跃的新兴的城市
But in Beijing, there's this kind of conflict between old and new residents.
但是北京就会有这种啊新旧居民的矛盾啊
On the surface, some people think that
表面上有些人认为啊
old Beijingers have made a fortune from demolishing and selling multiple properties.
这个老北京啊在一个拆迁八套房子都有钱
But in fact, most old Beijingers are poor.
但其实老北京啊是穷人
In reality, they form the majority.
其实是占多数的啊
It's the new Beijingers who are mostly wealthy.
新北京人富人是占多数的
Many people say, 'That's not right, though.'
很多人说哎这不对啊
How can it be that Beijingers
你北京人怎么着
at least have one property or something?
你也有一套房啊之类的
What do you think?
怎么样
We'll take our time and talk about it in this video.
咱们在这个视频里边慢慢说啊
In the next couple of episodes, I'll delve deeper into this topic.
我下两期还要继续从这个话题上深入啊
Why is Xiao Shen a study enthusiast?
为什么小申做题家
People who become second-generation students often suffer more. Then let's talk about the poor people's attitude towards money. Why do the poor actually love starting businesses? The rich, in fact, are quite cautious when it comes to doing things. I will go into specific details about these topics.
成为学二代的人通常会比较痛苦啊 然后我们再说穷人对钱的观念 为什么穷人其实爱创业 富人其实做事情很谨慎啊 我会讲具体的讲这些东西
Many poor people lack a clear understanding of money.
因为穷人对钱很多人没有概念啊
This is the content for the next three episodes.
这是最近三期的内容
Absolutely fantastic
非常精彩
So then
然后呢
I’ll insert a little ad at the end or in the middle
我会在这期结尾或者中间的地方
just to let you know where you can buy my book
穿插一个小广告
because some of the videos now
就是告诉大家那个在哪买我书的问题
Because there are some videos now
因为现在有有的视频
Many people don't follow live streams
有大家很多人不追直播
Watch only the video
只看视频
since we can’t post QR codes here on Bilibili
我会给大家进行指向性的那个什么
Because this counts as a business promotion
因为这算商家推广
But I can be in the video
但是我可以在视频里边
I can put a link in the pinned area
可以在置顶区链接
Many people generally think that Beijingers are wealthy
可以说呃其实很多人总认为就是北京人有钱
But in reality, many Beijingers aren’t rich at all
但其实很多北京人来讲呢并没有钱啊
For most people
大部分人来讲的话
They’re not like those who got compensated for their houses being demolished in the suburbs
就是并不是像啊郊区的那些拆迁户一样
Many people haven’t experienced that kind of demolition
很多人其实并没有拆迁啊
Some people are luckier
有人比较幸运
Like my brother, for example
比如你像我哥
He's rather fortunate in that regard.
他就比较幸运来讲
When it comes to his father,
他和父来讲呢
both he and his wife are only children.
这自己跟老婆呢都是独生子啊
Being only children,
独生子来讲呢
along with the grandparents on both sides, various relatives are all the same, everyone buys a house, and in the end, everything will end up in his name. So on average, one person ends up with three or four properties.
然后再加上这个等于说爷爷奶奶姥姥姥爷 然后各种各样的这个这个亲戚都是这样 大家都买房 然后最后呢最后都会最后落在自己身上 所以这一个人一个人平均的三四套房啊
Of course, this kind of situation is quite common.
当然是这种情况的比较多啊
However, to be honest
但是来讲的话
my situation is actually quite common
其实我这种情况呢也非常多啊
these two types of people are quite common
其实这两种人是非常多的
parents often don’t have separate rooms
就是呃父母都没有分房
and often, there’s only one house left in the family
然后很多时候就家里就最后剩了一套房
so this person tends to be quite extreme
所以这个人呢就比较极端
either they have several properties
要么就是好几套
or just one
要么就是一套
or even none at all
甚至有的没有的
some have always lived in public rental housing
就是那种从来就是公租房的
He has always lived in the old city of Beijing.
一直就住在四九城里的
But in fact, he doesn’t own the property rights.
但实际上他没有产权
After he demolished it,
他拆了以后
he didn’t have enough money to buy a place in the suburbs.
他那个钱也不够在郊区买
And for most Beijing residents,
而且大部分北京市民来讲的话
especially retired elderly men,
特别是退休老头儿老大爷
not everyone has a high pension.
他不不是每一个人的退休工资都很高
Some people have just an average pension.
有人的退休工资就一般
So besides the convenience of transportation,
所以他除了交通上比较便利啊
he can use his senior card to ride the bus and visit parks for free.
坐老年卡去公园上公交不不花钱以外
His actual purchasing power
他实际的购买能力
and the potential he can actually tap into are both very poor
跟他实际能拿出来的潜力都非常差
Many people don’t even have savings
很多人甚至没有积蓄
So the differences between individuals are quite significant Those who did business in the 90s or invested in real estate in the 2000s or those who made money from the stock market, they really hit the jackpot So some people have climbed up the wealth ladder but these people won’t exceed
所以人跟人之间的区别是特别大的 90年代做生意或者2000年炒房的那批人 炒股票的那些人赚了钱都赚了大钱的有 所以有些人的财富阶级就上去了 但这些人不会超过
800,000 people, for that matter
不会超过80万啊
in reality
实际来讲
Those who can currently afford assets worth over 4.5 million
你像现在能拿出450万资产以上的人
account for 720,000 in Beijing
在北京占72万
But how many millions of people are there in Beijing?
但北京一共有多少万人啊
Including the permanent residents
加上常住人口
and the floating population of 30 million
还有流动人口3000万
What percentage of these 30 million
这3000万中的百分之
720,000 out of these 30 million
这个3000万中的72
What kind of percentage does that make?
你算一个是什么样的百分比啊
If we divide by three
咱们除以三的话
it comes out to about 1.4
直接就是呃1.4
1.4%
1.4%的
It should be 1.4%, right?
应该是1.4%吧
Let me think, 2.4%
我想想2.4%
2.4%
2.4%
2.4 doesn't account for 2.4%
2.4没算2.4%这么一个人
So, as we often say,
所以来讲咱们常说啊
If you have a certain amount of assets,
如果你有多少多少万资产
you're in the top 2% in China,
就是中国的前2%
the top 1%,
前1%
or even the top 0.0001%.
前0%点几这东西来讲的话
One is your disposable income.
一个是你现金可支配收入
The other is the total amount of your assets.
一个是你的资产的总量
Including your house.
就算上房子
But in reality, many people, even when including their house,
但实际上很多人即使算上房子
their house is in the city center,
他的房子在中心区
they can't sell it and move to the suburbs afterward.
他也不可能卖掉以后去搬到包郊区
My family is in this situation.
你像我家就是这种情况
You can't sell and move to the suburbs.
你不可能卖掉以后搬到郊区郊区里哈
He has to go to school, and healthcare isn't convenient either. My parents are getting old too. They're not used to living in the suburbs either. But what if this generation is no longer around? I would definitely make that choice. I might not even move to the suburbs.
他上学呀 这个医疗都不方便啊 父母也老了 他们也不习惯去郊区生活 但是我呢如果他们啊这一代人不在了 那我肯定会做这种选择 我甚至不会搬到郊区
Perhaps I’d keep an apartment in Beijing to maintain the household registration.
可能北京可能留一套房作为户口的这个延续
But it’s also possible that I would rent out the entire place or this apartment,
但有可能完全就是就是整个或者这套房出租
or sell the house,
或者房子卖了
or keep one apartment,
或者留一套房
and then move to another city to live.
然后就去外地生活啊
Actually, in many places
其实很多地方
in terms of their living standards and consumption levels
他生活的标准和他的消费的等级来讲的话
when it comes to the feel of their daily life
就是从他的生活感觉来讲
it's much more comfortable than in Beijing
比北京要滋润的多
that's the reality for people in Beijing
这是北京人的实际情况
but when we talk about new Beijingers
但是我们说新北京人来讲的话
most of them are truly the backbone of Beijing's
其实大多数新北京人是真正北京的
prosperity and development
这个这个之所以兴旺发达繁荣的这个基础啊
the feeling is actually the opposite
其实感觉是反过来的
You remind me of my elementary and middle school days.
你像我的小学中学啊
Most of the university professors are not from Beijing.
大学的老师基本上没有北京本地的
They come from all over the country.
都是各个地方的啊
University students,
大学生
especially female teachers from Henan and Shandong provinces, are the most numerous.
特别是河南籍和山东籍的女教师数量是最多的
The reason Beijing has such advanced education,
北京之所以这么先进的教育
is largely due to these top universities being located here.
都是因为这几个大学其实在北京
So when we talk about it, the graduates of these universities, these outstanding graduates who come to Beijing's schools, they can be considered the best teachers in the country. the most experienced and the highest quality graduates come to these key schools in Beijing
所以来讲的话 这些大学的毕业生 这些优秀的毕业生来到北京的学校 那些老师可以说是全国最好的老师 最有经验的 而且是最优质的毕业生 来到北京这些重点的学校啊
for internships or work
实习啊或者工作
that's how it is
就是这样
and most people who buy houses in Beijing
而且来想大部分在北京买房的人
are actually new Beijingers
其实都是新北京人
and we're talking about all kinds of expensive properties in Beijing
而且是来讲我们说北京多贵的房子都有啊
wealthy people from all over the country are gradually
全国各地的富豪有钱人来慢慢来讲
constantly renewing the demographics of Beijing
北京人不停的迭代
It's the wealthier people
就是越有钱的人
who tend to live in the most expensive and central areas of Beijing
越住在北京的越核心越贵的房子里边
In reality, those who can afford homes priced at hundreds of thousands
实际上来讲真正能承受十几万房价
are often not locals
真正去买新房的人还是啊不是本地人
but people from all over the country
都是各个地方来的人居多啊
These people move into new districts
这些人住在了新的区
new areas
新的区域
and they are the ones buying new properties when they come on the market
新的房子开盘买的也是这些人
how many of them are old Beijing residents?
有几个是老北京的
Right?
对不对
How many people actually own the so-called three or eight apartments?
有几个人真正把自己所谓的啊三套房八套房
How many of those are in rural areas?
那有多少是农村房
How many are in the suburbs?
有多少是郊区房
How many are small-ownership properties?
有多少是小产权房
It's hard to say.
这都很难说的
So, those who are truly vibrant and capable,
所以那些真正有活力有实力的人
are the new Beijingers,
都是新北京人
with full benefits from major companies,
大厂拿齐全的啊
or those who run their own businesses,
自己做生意的
it's people like these.
就是这样的人
So we say, this concept in practice
所以我们说实际这概念
Often we feel that As a new Beijinger I am currently in the process of applying for residency through the points system I am still dealing with these procedures I am still paying off my loans I feel quite insignificant There's no need for that Absolutely no need for that You are the true owner of this city
很多时候觉得啊 我作为新北京人 我作为啊现在还在办积分落户啊 现在还在办这些 我还在还着贷款 我觉得自己很卑微 没有没有这个必要 完全没有这个必要 你才是这个城市的主人
The housing prices in this city are maintained by you.
这个城市的房价是你维持的
The rental values in this city are also maintained by you.
这个城市的租金价值是你维持的
The educational standards in this city are maintained by you.
这城市教育水平是你维持的
The primary consumers in this city
这个城市的消费主力
are also sustained by you.
也是你维持的
The genuine old Beijingers,
真正的老北京人
like me,
你像我这个
of course, my generation is the post-80s, post-50s, and so on.
当然我这代人是八零后五零后这种状态啊
Post-80s, post-50s, post-10s, and so forth.
八零后五零后一零后啊
So, in terms of actual purchasing power,
所以实际的消费能力来讲
You see, I wear four white shirts every day.
你看我一天就是白衬衫四件
And five pairs of black shorts with black stripes.
黑衬黑的踢那个跨栏呃五件
Then I change every day.
然后呢天天换
You won’t even notice that I have 334 sets of shorts.
你也看不见我那个短裤就334套
And just one pair of shoes.
然后一一双鞋
So you see, I dress like this every day.
所以你看我天天就是这种打扮啊
Wearing flip-flops or sneakers.
穿个拖鞋或者穿个球鞋
That’s pretty much my style.
就这么一种打扮
Riding a small electric scooter.
骑个小电驴
My spending power is actually quite limited
我的消费能力其实很差
The main money should be spent on children's consumption.
主要的钱就是就是让孩子去消费啊
When it comes to parents, their spending power is also quite low.
父母来讲消费能力也很差
So, such people don't contribute much to the economy.
所以这样的人对经济他没有贡献啊
You see, I could easily afford the Xiaomi 13 Ultra every day,
你看我天天明明能买小米苏7ultra
but I insist on buying the BYD Dolphin. And it’s still the lower-end model. It might even be second-hand. So that’s how it is. Actually, speaking of savings, the more you save, the better. The less willing you are to spend money, the more you feel it's being used up. Because you know once something is used, it's gone.
非要去买比亚迪海鸥 就是这样还是低配版 可能还是二手 所以就是这样 越其实来讲 你积蓄的越多 你越不愿意去花这个钱去消耗它 因为你知道消耗的东西就没了
Unless money can generate more money.
除非钱能再生钱
In what circumstances can money generate more money?
对什么样的情况是钱能生钱
How should one spend their wealth?
该怎么样消耗自己的财富
To acquire new wealth.
获得新的财富
How exactly should one maintain the lifestyle they had during school?
到底该怎样维持自己的上学时候的生活
Marriage life.
婚姻生活
Economic life.
经济生活
Look at this book of mine, it’s a must-have.
你看我这本必坑啊
Now you can visit Xiao Yinfu's conifer culture page.
现在你们可以去小音符的针叶文化
The authentic conifer culture page.
真正的针叶子叶针叶文化
It's the enterprise account of my little note.
就是我的那个小音符的企业号啊
Head to his Douyin store and download
去他的抖店下载
Or you can search for 'Bikong Rongzhen' on Taobao.
或者大家可以在呃淘宝上搜索B坑容振啊
Bikong Rongzhen.
B坑容镇呵
Just writing 'Bikong' might not lead you to me,
就是你光写避坑可能不是我
and just writing 'Rongzhen' might not either,
光写容振可能也不是我
but searching for 'Bikong Rongzhen' will find me.
但是避坑容忍就能搜到了
It's about the book 'Avoiding Pitfalls'.
就是关于避坑这本书啊
Shandong Publishing House
山东出版社啊
This Jinan Publishing House is not the Shandong Publishing House.
这个济南出版社不是山东出版社
The Jinan Publishing House releases the B edition.
济南出版社出的是B坑
But what you're buying now has this laser edge
而你现在买的是这个这个有这激光边儿啊
With that colorful and changing ink And also My autograph Buying this book is especially beneficial for those with insufficient knowledge Families with weak financial awareness
有那个五彩斑斓的变色的那个油墨 然后还有这个这个这个这个这个这个 我的亲笔签名啊 买这本书其实就是特别是那种认知不足 家庭的这种金钱观念不强的人
Reading this book will definitely help
你看这本书绝对能好
Especially since you're not married yet
特别是你现在没结婚
Still single
还没结婚
Haven't bought a house
没买房
Just graduated
刚毕业
It's a perfect fit for you
非常适合你
It's particularly suitable during your college years
在上大学的阶段非常适合啊
Middle School Students might find it a bit premature.
中学生可能看的有点早啊
People my age might be too late
岁数跟我一样大的人可能就来不及了
So it doesn't really matter
所以无所谓啊
My core audience and reader base
我的这个核心的这个观众的读者群呢
Are we talking about the post-90s or post-00s?
还是九零后零零后啊
So let's carry on with this topic.
然后我们说继续说这个问题
Actually, you need to hold your head up high.
其实你就完全要抬起头来做
Because, you know, people in Beijing,
因为实际上北京人啊
especially old Beijingers, don't have as many wealthy individuals.
特别是老北京没有那么多有钱的
Of course, there are rich people,
有钱的人肯定是有
but the less fortunate don't appear as wealthy.
但是没钱的人他不显有钱的人
They love to show off.
他爱险啊
Particularly for some people,
特别是有些人来讲
it's all about saving face.
他因为有面知道他他有面子
So he's willing to write.
所以他就是愿意写
But in reality, for most people,
但实际上大部分人来人来讲的话
Actually, there are quite a lot of people like me.
其实我这种状态的人还是非常多的啊
In large families,
多子女家庭啊
There are more people,
人也比较多啊
And they tend to do some basic work,
然后呢从事一些基础工作
Such people are really very numerous. Some may not have any descendants. Not everyone has a thriving family. Of course, there are also those who are only children of only children. They are all from Beijing. This kind of person will become increasingly wealthy.
就是这样的人非常非常的多 有些人你可能他可能那后代没有人了 不是人丁非常兴旺了 当然也有那种独生子女接独生子女啊 都是北京人 就这种他会越过越富
So in many cases,
所以很多的时候来讲
the choice of marriage and the inheritance of wealth later on,
婚姻的选择和你后来的这个财富的传承
are directly related.
有直接的关系
How you choose your marriage,
你婚姻怎么选择
what your family structure is like,
你家庭结构是怎么样的
how many properties your parents leave you,
父母给你留几套房
that’s why there’s no such thing as a dowry among Beijingers.
所以所谓的北京人没有彩礼一说
Because there is this material foundation, after all.
因为有这些东西物质基础在嘛
So it doesn’t really matter whether there’s a dowry or not.
所以无所谓彩礼不彩礼
If the couple has a harmonious relationship,
如果两个人夫妻关系又和谐
they might even have a second or third child.
生个二三胎
But in such a scenario,
但是像这样的情况下
they are considered the lucky ones.
属于幸运的人
However, many people are not as fortunate.
但是很多人来讲可能没有那么幸运
Those who truly bear the heavy burden of a mortgage,
真正来讲背负特别强力的房贷的人
are also new Beijingers.
其实也是新北京人
But those who have the means to buy properties outright,
但是能有权利全款去买那些房子的人
Not these old Beijingers
不是这些老北京人
So in terms of economic vitality, they are the new Beijingers
所以在经济活力上来讲是新北京人
Or you could say the newer Beijingers
或者你说新新北京人
Because we refer to those born after 1949 as new Beijingers
因为我们把49年以后的人
I call them new Beijingers
我称为新北京人
Now they are the newer Beijingers
现在是新新北京人
But actually, new Beijingers should be counted from the year 2000
但其实新北京人你应该按2000年来算
Right?
对不对
According to the period after the 2008 Olympics
按这个08年奥运会之后
Because after that, there weren't as many people coming in
因为那个时候后边的人就没有那么多
So-called demolition households stock investors and people who speculate in real estate before and after 2008 or you could say before 2015 after 2015, there were two different approaches but everyone's perception is different so it doesn't really matter
所谓的拆迁户 股民 还有炒房子的人了 2008年之前跟2008年之后 或者你按2015年之前 2015年之后就是两种分散方法 但是呢每个人的感觉是不一样的 所以无所谓
but I'm just saying, these so-called
但是我就是说你这些啊所谓的啊
people often modestly refer to themselves as small-town problem solvers
经常大家以这种小镇做题家自谦
But actually, I want to say that the best way to speak is in Beijing dialect.
但实际上啊我要说北京话最好的
How many graduates does C9 produce each year?
C9每年有多少毕业生
How many graduates do the 985 and 211 universities produce each year?
985211每年有多少毕业生
These true graduates from 982, 211, and C9 universities.
这些真正的98211C9的毕业生啊
The employees in these large enterprises.
这些大型企业中的职工啊
The excellent bosses of these cross-border companies.
这些优秀的跨境企业的这些老板啊
These local county Brahmans
这些各地的县城婆罗门啊
These people who come to Beijing to develop.
来北京发展的这些人
They might have earned a lot of money back home.
可能家乡赚了很多钱
Then they come to Beijing to buy houses.
然后来北京买房子
Then, just like that, they become Beijingers.
然后一下就摇身一变就变成北京人了
These are the new Beijingers.
这是新北京人
It's because of these people,
正是因为这些人
who have injected new economic vitality into Beijing,
给北京注入了新的这个经济活力
not the old Beijingers.
而不是这些老北京
When it comes to the old Beijingers,
老北京来讲的话
their spending power
他的消费能力
and earning capacity are limited.
他的挣钱能力都有限
Their salaries are only so much,
那工资就那么多啊
and their pensions are only so much.
那个退休金就那么多
He might have been affected by the demolition.
他有可能因为这个拆迁的原因
But these people believe that those who truly made a fortune from the demolition are few. Among the residents of Beijing, this group is relatively small. Most are villagers. For years, due to household registration issues, they were at the bottom of the socioeconomic ladder because of various reasons. These people have since turned their fortunes around.
但这部分人相信我真正拆迁赚到大钱的人 在北京的市民里边占的数量比较少 大部分是村民 就是以前多少年因为户口 因为各种各样的东西处于经济社会中的底层的 这些人后来翻身了
Is that right?
是这样啊
So, to put it another way,
所以来讲的话
we can say that the real turning point was in 1949.
咱们说真正翻身还是49年
How should I put this?
大家整个的这个怎么说呢
There have been some changes.
变化了一下啊
This social stratum has undergone a tremendous transformation.
这个整个这个阶层发生了翻天覆地的变化
This is the most significant change.
这个是最大的变化
But when we talk about changes in the economy,
但是我们说经济上面的变化来讲
The change in academic opportunities came with the restoration of the national unified examination for admissions to general universities and colleges in 1978.
学识上的变化是78年恢复高考啊
In 77, the restoration of national unified examination for admissions to general universities and colleges took place.
77年恢复高考啊
Many people are different now,
很多人是不一样的
So to speak,
所以来讲的话
People often talk about the 1960s
咱们说很多人就是常说60年代
People from the 70s
70年代的人啊
You know, last time a lot of people were hit hard
你像上期啊一打击打击一大片
and many got upset
然后很多人生气
but actually, people from the 60s and 70s were quite fortunate
但其实六七十年代的人是非常幸运的
they got university placements
大学赶上分配
and they also caught the housing reform wave
然后住房的时候也赶上改革啊
gaining their first batch of commercial housing
然后有了第一批自己的商品房的积累
they were right on the pulse of the times
然后很多东西都踩在了时代的脉搏之上
and things went relatively smoothly
然后比较顺利
whereas the 80s generation might have had a tougher time
八零后可能就倒霉一点啊
Nothing was caught up with
什么东西都没赶上
But the economic development of any country
但是哪个国家的经济发展
Always has a generation with relatively more advantages
永远有相对比较优势的一代
There is also a generation that is relatively more unfortunate But it's definitely not the majority Each era has its own outstanding individuals Each era also has its own general trend It's not that the majority of people in any era are a certain way So you are bound to be that way
有相对比较倒霉的一代 但绝对不是都是大多数 每个时代都有自己的佼佼者 每个时代也有自己的一个整体的一个倾向 并不是说每一个时代的人大多数是什么样 你就一定是什么样
Nor are you destined to follow the majority
也不是说你一定会跟随大多数
But each era has its own mark.
但是每个时代都有自己的烙印啊
So when we talk about this, it is
所以来讲这个就是啊
Economically and socially, those from the sixties and seventies are clearly more successful.
经济社会上更成功的明显是六七十年代的人
But if we look ahead another decade,
但是我们说再过10年
Another ten years down the line,
再过10年
When the previous generation fades away
等下一上一代人在消亡了
For this generation, speaking
这一代人来讲
People from the eighties and nineties will become the backbone of society.
八九十年代的人变成了这个社会的中坚力量呢
There might be some new tycoons emerging,
可能又会出一些新的富豪
And things will be different again.
又是不一样的
So society is always moving forward
所以这社会永远在滚滚向前
Whoever speaks at this moment
谁在这个时候来讲的话
We often say achieving success before the age of 30
我们常说30岁之前就获得成功
Is actually not an easy feat
其实是不太容易的事
Unless you're a prodigy
除非你是特别天才
Those who have a strong economic foundation
特别有这个经济基础的人啊
But for most people, it might not be that easy
但其实其他人来讲可能没有那么的容易
So if you buy this book of mine
所以其实你们买我这本B坑的话
You can see the various life trajectories of different people
可以看到各种人的这个人生轨迹是什么样的
Why you want to take this path
你为什么要走这样条路
Do you have a path dependency?
你是否有路径依赖
Take some time to think about it.
都好好的思考一下
So, many people, throughout their parents' lives,
所以因为很多人他父母这一生
they haven't figured out their main purpose.
他没有告诉他自己主要的是什么
Actually, you're already among the best.
其实你已经是佼佼者了
Think about it, you came from a very poor place, or a place with a smaller population, or an economically underdeveloped area, and through your own hard work and study, you've made it through the college entrance exam, which isn't entirely fair.
你想你从一个很穷的地方 或者一个人口比较少的地方 或者一个经济不发达的地方 通过自己的学习努力啊 经过了高考的这种不是那么的公平的
In terms of this method of distribution
这种分配的这种方式来讲
you've also secured a top ranking in your province
你又在你的省啊拿到了前茅的名次
or you got in through the Strong Foundation Program
或者你通过强基计划
various training programs
各种各样的培养计划
you got admitted to Tsinghua or Peking University
你考到了清华北大
you got into the C9 universities
你考到了C9
you got into the 985 and 211 institutions
你考到了98211
and became a pillar of the community in Beijing
然后变成了北京的这个啊中流砥柱
you also want to stay here after graduation
你毕业以后也想留在这里
to live here
为了在这里生活
So, to talk about it,
所以来讲的话
there's actually no need,
其实没有必要
just lift your chest up,
你就抬起挺抬起胸
stand tall and proud,
挺穷挺胸抬头做人
those people who act tough in front of you in Beijing,
那些很多人跟你在面前吊逼吊的北京人
they're not really that many beneficiaries of demolition compensation,
其实他没有真正多少拆迁户
it's more of a sense of local survival crisis,
他是一种本地生存危机的感觉
in this regard,
可能这一点上来讲的话
the feeling might be more pronounced among Shanghainese,
上海人的感觉可能更明显一些
of course, I'm not a resident of Shanghai.
当然我不是上海市民啊
My relatives in Shanghai are all old Shanghainese.
上海我家的这亲戚也都是老上海
So when I talk about it,
所以来讲的话
I might look at the issue from their perspective,
我可能从他们的角度来讲去看这个问题呢
but I might not see it as deeply,
可能看的不是很深
since I haven’t lived in Shanghai for a long time.
因为我没有咱们在上海长期生活过啊
It’s different.
是不一样
But I think from the perspective of someone from Beijing,
但是我觉得从北京人来讲的话
the conflicts between locals and outsiders have been decreasing more in recent years. In the past, before Guo Degang became famous, There were still some contradictions in that era. But as time went on, through the generations,
本地外地矛盾更多来讲 近年来是越来越少了 以前可能郭德纲没成名 那个时代还有一点这方面的矛盾 但是越来越到后边几代以后
people became more and more different.
人与人之间的不一样啊
People noticed that those with purchasing power were mostly newcomers to Beijing.
大家发现有购买力的人基本都是新北京人
Moreover, internet giants became increasingly powerful.
而且来讲呢互联网那些大厂越来越厉害了啊
There was a distinction between those in these companies and those outside.
这个企业跟不是企业当中的人
Compared to the locals, Beijingers relatively speaking,
因为北京人相对来讲的话
had a stronger capability in their jobs,
拿的那份工作的能力来讲
compared to all those not from Beijing,
跟整个所有的不是北京来讲
in terms of the skill levels of those born locally.
本地出生的这些人的这个能力水平来讲
He must be hanging upside down.
他肯定是倒挂的
He definitely is.
他肯定是啊
As they say, the latecomer often surpasses the early bird.
怎么说后来者居上
So many people complain about Beijing, you know,
所以很多人就是嘴里边啊骂着北京
or they have a sense of inferiority when they talk about it.
或者说嘴里边有一种自卑的感觉
But in reality, gradually, you become what you...
但实际上慢慢的你就变成了啊
You hate someone,
你恨谁
and in the end, you turn into that person.
最后就成为了谁
It’s such a dramatic turn of events.
就是这样一个非常戏剧化的一种感觉
For these people, it’s genuine.
而这些人来讲是真的
The pillar of Beijing
北京的中流砥柱
rather than us old residents
而不是我们这些老的市民
So our ultimate fate
所以我们的这个最终的结局呢
might be gradually moving away from the city center
来可能就是慢慢的可能就从城市中心搬开
either to the suburbs
要么到郊区啊
or to other places
要么到外地
gradually being washed away by the tide of time Of course, I'm talking about the second economic choice Often you need to find a city that suits you Your wealth level How much money you have Determines where you should live If you don’t come back in the future When you have money You can return to Beijing
慢慢的就随着时代的洪流就被冲刷掉了啊 当然来讲我说经济的二次选择 很多的时候来讲 你要去适合你的城市 你的财富等级 你有多少钱 你就应该在什么地方生活 如果你以后不来 有钱了 你可以再回到北京
Now that you don’t have money
你现在没钱了
You should leave Beijing
你看你就应该离开北京
However
但是这样来讲
Many people can’t accept this viewpoint
这个观点很多人是接受不了的
Of course, what we're looking for is a comfortable and high-quality life.
当然我们说我们要找的是舒适优质的生活
If you just want to have some fried dough rings in the morning,
如果你就是希望早上吃点焦圈
and a bowl of soy milk,
然后喝碗豆汁儿
then you should stay in the city without moving.
那你就待在城里边别动
But living like this is definitely not a high-quality life that comes from wealth.
但是你这样绝对不是财富之下产生的
a high-quality life.
一种优质的生活
Naturally speaking,
当然来讲
people have different perceptions and feelings about this.
人与人之间的这个认知跟这个感受是不一样的
So we say,
所以我们就说啊
we truly need to thank all the new Beijingers.
真正我们要感谢所有的新的北京人
Willing to stay in Beijing
愿意留在北京
Willing to build this city with hard work
愿意愿意用自己的辛勤努力建设这座城市
It's actually quite challenging
其实是非常的不容易
All your efforts
你的所有的这些付出
Benefit everyone
其实大家都一起收益
We all benefit
一起获益的
The original residents should thank you
其实这些原住民是应该感谢你啊
If you've ever been in Beijing
如果这个你曾经在北京
And experienced the pain of regional discrimination
感受到这个地域歧视的这个苦来讲的话
I apologize on behalf of everyone
那老哥跟你说一声抱歉啊
Because they don't know any better
因为他们不懂事儿啊
Don't stoop to their level
别跟他们一般见识
They gradually faded away with the tides of time
他们也随着时代洪流慢慢也就退去了
But many of the old Beijingers actually understand this very well They know it in their hearts Everyone works hard So I still suggest that older folks Even though public transportation is free for you
但其实很多北京大爷是非常明白这件事的啊 他心里是明白的啊 大家的上班很辛苦 所以我还是建议老年人啊 就是你虽然公交那个出行那个免费
Try not to travel during rush hour
但是尽量不要在上班时间
Don't inconvenience these hardworking people
不要跟这些辛勤劳作的人来讲的话
to take up people's commuting time
去挤占人家上班的这个这个交通时间
but I know that some vegetables won't be available if you're too late
但我知道有些菜时间长了就没没地儿抢了
you could go by electric scooter, right?
那你可以骑电动车去嘛对吧
if that doesn't work
实在不行
I can ride the electric scooter and take you along
我骑电动车推着你去
so many things are like this
所以很多事情就是这样
and many of the conflicts in Beijing's development
然后很多北京发展的矛盾
such as the issue with license plates
比如车牌的问题之类的
these are part of the era's progress
这个东西是时代发展
a necessary phase of urbanization
城市化必然的阶段
This thing has nothing to do with anyone.
这个东西跟谁跟谁之间的并没有关系
So, for any country's prosperity and development,
所以任何国家兴旺发达来讲
new immigrants are needed.
都是需要新的移民涌入的啊
And among these new immigrants,
而这些新的移民里边来讲
Chinese immigrants,
属于中国的这些移民来讲的话
have the highest cultural literacy,
文化素质最高
and the strongest work ethic,
劳动能力最强啊
so they are very hardworking and law-abiding,
所以非常勤奋又非常的守法
and they won't change the local culture,
又不会改变本地的文化
these are Chinese immigrants.
就是中国移民
Whether it's moving abroad,
不管是移到外国的
or to various major cities,
还是移到各种大城市的啊
this is a very powerful force in China,
这是一个中国的非常强大的一个
from a human perspective, the power of urbanization. So, thank you to all those who are willing to contribute to building Beijing, thank you for your contributions to this city. You are here, and you are the new masters.
从人的上角度上来讲的话 城市化的力量 所以呢感谢我们这些 愿意建设北京的这些学子们 感谢你们为这座城市做的贡献啊 你们来了 其实就是新的主人